In this segment, we're gonna look at the
Diffie-Hellman protocol, which is our
本节我们看Diffie-Hellman协议
first practical key exchange mechanism. So
let me remind you of the settings. Our
这是我们的第一个实用的密钥交换机制 让我来为大家讲一下目前的设定
friends here, Alice and Bob, have never
met and yet they wanna exchange a shared
我们的朋友Alice和Bob素未谋面 却想要交换一个共享密钥
secret key that they can then use to
communicate securely with one another.
然后他们可以使用这个密钥来用于相互安全通信
In this segment and the next, we're only
gonna be looking at eavesdropping
这两节我们只看对窃听攻击的安全性
security. In other words, we only care
about eavesdroppers. The attackers are
换句话说 我们只关心窃听攻击
actually not allowed to tamper with data
in the network. They're not allowed to
攻击者不能篡改网络中的数据
inject packets. They're not allowed to
change packets in any way. All they do is
他们不能篡改数据 不能以任何方式改数据包
to just eavesdrop on the traffic. And at
the end of the protocol, the key exchange
他们只能窃听网络流量 在密钥协议的最后
protocol our friends Alice and Bob should
have a shared secret key but the attacker
我们的朋友Alice和Bob应该有一个共享密钥
namely the eavesdropper has no idea what
that key's gonna be. In the previous
但窃听攻击者无法知道交换的密钥是什么
segment we looked at a key segment called
Merkle puzzles. That's just using block
上一节我们看了所谓的Merkle谜题的协议
ciphers or hash functions. And I showed
you that there that basically the attacker
只使用分组密码和哈希函数 我还告诉大家
has a quadratic gap compared to the
participants. In other words if the
攻击者有一个平方鸿沟 相比于参与者 换句话说
participants spent time proportional to N
the attacker can break the protocol in
如果参与者花了与N成正比的时间 那么攻击者
time proportional to N squared. And as a
result that protocol is to insecure to be
能在与N成正比的时间破解这个协议 因此这个协议从应用角度来看
considered practical. In this segment we
are going to ask whether we can do the
是不安全的 本节我们研究 我们能否做同样的事情
same thing but now we'd like to achieve an
exponential gap between the attacker's
但现在我们能获得一个指数即鸿沟 横在
work Ended up in the participant's work.
In other words, Alice and Bob might do
攻击者和参与者的工作之间 换句话说 Alice和Bob
work proportional to N, but to break the
protocol the attacker is gonna have to do
可以做与N成正比的工作 但为了破解这个协议
work proportional to some exponential in
N. So now there's an exponential gap
攻击者必须做与N成正比的某个指数级成正比的工作量
between the participants work and the
attacker's work. So as I said in the
现在 在参与者和攻击者值的工作之间有一条指数级鸿沟 那么如我上节所说
previous segment we can't achieve this
exponential gap from blog ciphers like AES
我们不能获得这个指数级鸿沟 仅凭像AES或SHA-256这样的分组密码技术
or SHA-256. We have to use hard problems
that have more structure than just those
我们必须使用拥有比对称原型更多结构的难解问题
symmetric primitives. And so instead what
we're gonna do is use a little bit of algebra.
那我们使用一点代数
In this segment I'm gonna
describe the Diffie-Hellman protocol very
本节我将描述Diffie-Hellman协议
concretely and somewhat informally. When
we're gonna come back to Diffie-Hellman next week
以很具体的形式 不是很形式化 下周还是回到Diffie-Hellman协议
and we're gonna describe the protocol more
abstractly and we're gonna do a much more
我们将更为抽象的描述这个函数 对这个协议进行更为严格的安全分析
rigorous security analysis of this
protocol. Okay, so how does Diffie-Hellman
那么Diiffie-Hellman协议是如何工作的呢？
work? What we're gonna do is, first of
all, we're gonna fix some large prime
首先 我们选某个固定的大质数
which I'm gonna call p. Actually p I'll
usually use to denote primes. And you
记之为p 我通常用p表示质数
should be thinking of really gigantic
primes. Like, primes that are made up of
大家应该把它想象成非常大的质数 比如
600 digits are so. And just for those of
you who like to think in binary, a 600
有600个十进制的质数 如果大家喜欢用二进制
digit prime roughly corresponds to about
2000 bits. So just writing down the prime
600个十进制大约相当于2000个二进制
takes about two kilo bits of data. And
then we're also gonna fix an integer g
写下了约2000个质数 然后我们选一个固定的质数g
that happens to live in the range one to
p. So these values p and g are parameters
g正好在从1到p的范围中 这里的p和g
of the Diffie-Hellman protocol. They are
chosen once and they're fixed forever. Now
是Diffie-Hellman协议的参数 它们一经选择就不再改变
the protocol works as follow. So here's
our friends Alice and Bob. So what Alice's
现在这个协议如下工作 我们的朋友Alice和Bob
going to do is she's gonna starts off by
choosing some random number a in the range 1 to p-1
开始时Alice选择某个随机数 范围是从1到p-1
And then she is gonna compute
the number g to the power of a modulo p.
然后她将计算g^a mod p
Okay, so she computes this exponention,
and reduces the result modular the prime p.
她计算这个指数 然后将结果取质数p的模
And we're actually going to see how to
compute this efficiently the next module,
下一章中我们将看到如何有效地计算这个有限域上的指数
so for now just believe me that this
computation can be done efficiently.
现在请大家相信我 这是可以有效计算的
Now, let's call capital A the result of this
value. So, what Alice will do is she will
现在我们计算这个结果
send capital A over to Bob. Now Bob is
going to do the same thing. He's going to
Alice将这个结果传送给Bob 他将做同样的事情
choose a random number b in the range 1
to p-1. He's going to compute g to
他选择一个随机数b 范围从1到p-1
the b module of p and let's call this
number B and he's going to send this
Bob计算g^b mod p 我们记结果为B
number B over to Alice. So Alice sends A
to Bob. Bob sends B. To Alice. And now
然后Bob把B发送给Alice 那么Alice发送了A给Bob Bob发送了B给Alice
they claim that they can generate a shared
secret key. So what's a shared secret key?
现在他们宣布 他们已经共享了一个密钥 那么这个共享密钥是什么
Well, it's defined as. Let's call it
KAB. And it's basically defined as the
我们来定义它 记之为K_AB
value g to the power of a times b. Now the
amazing observation of Diffie-Hellman had
K_AB的定义为g^ab mod D 现在Diffie-hellman在1976年的一个惊人的观察结果是
back in 1976 is that in fact both parties
can compute this value g to the ab.
事实上双方都可以计算这个值g^ab mod p
So let's see, Alice can compute this value
because she can take her value B that she
来看 Alice可以计算这个值 因为她可以取值B
received from Bob. She can take this value
B, raise it to the power of a and, let's
B是Bob给她的 她可以取值B 计算B^a mod p
see, what she'll get is g to the b to the
power of b. And by the rules of
她会获得g^ab mod p
exponentiation, g to the power of b to the
power of a is equal to g to the ab. Bob
根据指数规则 （g^b)^a=(g^a)^b mod p
turns out, can do something similar, so
his goal is to compute g to the a to the b,
Bob实际可以做类似的事 那么他的目标是计算(g^a)^b mod p
which again, is g to the ab, so both
Alice and Bob will have computed KAB, and
答案依然是g^ab mod p 所以Alice和Bob都可以计算K_AB
let me ask you, how does Bob actually
compute this quantity g to the ab?
我问大家 Bob是怎么计算g^ab mod p的？
Well so all he does is he takes the value A that
he received from Alice and he raises it to
他取Alice给他的A
his own secret b and that gives him the
shared secret g to the ab. So you can see
计算A^b mod p 就得到了共享密钥g^ab mod p
now that both parties even though they
seemingly computed different values. In
大家可以看到 尽管双方计算的值不一样
fact they both end up with the same value
namely g ab module p. I should mention by
事实上他们会得到同样的值g^ab mod p
the way that Martie Hellman and Wig
Diffiie came up with this protocol back in
我应该顺便提到 Martin和Wig Diffie于1976年提出这一协议
1976. Martie Hellman was a professor here
at Stanford and Wig Diffie was his
当时Matrin Hellman是斯坦福的教授 而Whg Diffie是他的研究生
graduate student. They came up with this
protocol and this protocol really changed
他们提出的这个协议真正改变了全世界
the world. In that it introduced this new
age in cryptography. Where now it's not just
它开创了密码学的新纪元
about developing block ciphers but it's
actually about designing algebraic
现在不仅是关于开发分组密码 而且是关于
protocols that have properties like the
one we see here. So you notice that what
设计基于代数的协议 使之拥有类似我们这里的性质
makes this protocol works is basically
properties of exponentiation. Namely that,
大家注意，这个协议顺利工作的本质原因是指数的代数性质
g to the b to the power of a is the same
as g to the a to the power of b, okay?
即（g^b）^a=(g^a)^b
These are just properties of
exponentiations. Now when I describe a
这些是指数的性质。现在当我描述
protocol like the one I just showed you.
The real question that should be in your
一个像我刚才展示给大家的协议时，大家应该想到的真正问题
mind is not why the protocol works. In
other words, it's very easy to verify
不是这个协议为什么能工作。换句话说，很容易验证这点
that, in fact, both Alice and Bob end up
with the same secret key. The bigger
事实上，Alice和Bob最后会得到同样的密钥
question is why is this protocol secure?
In other words, why is it that an
更重要的问题是，为什么这个协议是安全的？换句话说，为什么一个窃听者
eavesdropper cannot figure out the same
shared key due to the AB that both Alice
无法根据双方发出的A、B，解出共享密钥？
and Bob computed by themselves? So let's
analyze this a little bit, then, like I
让我们稍作分析，如我所说
said, we're gonna do a much more in-depth
analysis next week. But, let's, for now,
下周我们进行更进一步的分析
just see intuitively why this protocol is
gonna be secure. Well, what does the
现在我们先直观地看一下问什么这个协议是安全的
eavesdropper see? Well, he sees the prime
and the generator. These are just fixed
窃听者能看到什么？他能看到质数和生成元（这里质数是指上文的p，生成元是指g）
forever and everybody knows who they are.
He also sees the value that Alice sent to
这些值是永远固定不变的，每个人都知道它们。攻击者还能看到Alice发给Bob的值A
Bob, namely this capital A. And he sees
the value that Bob sent to Alice, namely
他还能看到Bob发给Alice的值B
this capital B. And the question is, can
the, can the eavesdropper compute g to the
问题是，窃听者能计算出g^ab mod p
ab just given these four values? So more
generally, what we can do is we can define
仅根据这四个值吗？更一般地
this Diffie-Hellman function. So we'll say
that the Diffie-Hellman function is defined
我们可以定义这个Diffie-Hellman函数。我们说Diffie-Hellman函数
based on some value g. And the question is
given g to the a, and g to the b. Can you
定义在某个值g上，问题是，给定g^a和g^b
compute g to the ab? And what we're
asking is how hard is it to compute this
能否计算g^ab?我们在问，计算这个
function module over very large prime p.
Remember p was something like 600 digits.
很大的质数模p乘法群上的函数，有多困难？记得p大约有600个十进制位
So the real question we need to answer is
how hard is this, is this Diffie-Hellman
所以真正的问题是，这个Diffie-Hellman函数
function? So let me show you what's known
about this. So suppose the prime happens
有多难解？我来告诉大家目前已知的事实。介绍这个质数正好有n位长
to be n bits long. Okay, so in our case
say n is 2,000 bits. It turns out the best
在我们这里比如说n=2000位
实际上计算Diffie-Hellman函数，已知最好的算法
Diffie–Hellman function. Is actually a
known algorithm for computing the
more general algorithm that computes the
discrete log function, which we're gonna
是一个更为一般的算法，用来计算离散对数函数
talk about next week. But for now, let's
just say that this algorithm computes a
我们下周讨论它。但现在，我们就说这个算法
Diffie-Hellman function. The algorithm is
called a general number field sieve. I'm
能计算Diffie-Hellman函数。这个算法叫做普通数域筛法
not gonna describe how it works, although
if you'd want to hear how it works, let me
我这里不描述它是如何工作的，不过大家想听一听它是如何工作的
know, and that could be one of the special
topics that we cover at the end of the
告诉我们，我们会在课程的最后开一个特殊专题
course. But the interesting thing is that
it's running time is exponential in
有趣的是，这个算法的运行时间是指数级的
roughly the cube root of n. In other
words, the running time is roughly e to
指数大约是n的立方根。换句话说，运行时间
the power of o of cube root of n. So in
fact the exact expression for the running
大约是e的n的立方根次方。事实上这个算法的运行时间的严格表达式
time, of this algorithm is much more
complicated than this. I'm deliberately
要比这个复杂得多
simplifying it here just to kind of get
the point across. The point that I want to
我故意简化了，以求直击要点
emphasize is that in fact, this is not
quite an exponential time algorithm.
我想强调的一点是，事实上，这不是严格的指数时间的算法
Exponential would be e to the power of n.
This is sometimes called a sub-exponential
指数时间是指e^n。这个算法有事叫做亚指数算法
algorithm because the exponent is really
just proportional to the cube root of n,
因为这里的指数项正比于n的立方根
as opposed to linear n. What this says is
that even though this problem is quite
而不是n。这说明即使这个问题很难
difficult, it's not really an exponential
time problem. The running time in the
他也不是真正的指数级时间的问题
exponent is gonna be just proportional to
the cube root of n. So let's look at some
运行时间的指数是与n的立方根成正比的
examples. Suppose I happen to be looking
at a modulus that happens to be about a
那么我们来看几个例子。假设我正好在看一个模
thousand bits long. What this algorithm
says is that we can solve the
有大于一千位长，这个算法是说
Diffie-Hellman problem in time that's
approximately e to the qube root of 1,024.
我们可以解决Diffie-Hellman的问题，以时间大约是e的1024的立方根次方
Now this is not really correct, in fact
there are more constants in the exponent.
这不是很准确，事实上指数上有一些常数项
But again, just to get, the point across,
we can say that the running time would be
但只看要点的话，我们可以说算法的运行时间
roughly e to the qube root of 1,024; which
is actually very small, roughly e to the 10.
大约是e的1024的立方根次方，这个值其实很小，大约是e的10次方（约22000）
So the simple example shows you that
if you have a sub-exponential algorithm,
这个简单的例子告诉大家，如果你有一个亚指数级算法
you see that even if the problem is quite
large, like 1,000 bits. Because of the
大家看到即使这个问题规模很大，比如1000位
cube root effect the exponent actually is not
that big overall. Now to be honest I'm
因为这个立方根的作用，其实总体并没有那么大
actually lying here. General number field
sieve actually have many other
说实话我就讲到这里了。普通数域筛法
constants in the exponents so in fact this
is not going to be ten at all. It's
在指数上有很多其他常数，不如事实上这个根本不是10
actually going to be something like 80.
Because of various constants in the
而是类似于80的样子。因为指数上的各种常数
exponents. But nevertheless but you see
the problem is much harder than say 2 to
但是大家看到这个问题依然比2的1000次方（这里讲反了。筛法降低了问题复杂性）
the 1000. Even though describing it takes
1,000 bits, solving it does not take time
困难的多。尽管描述它需要1000位，但解决它
to the 1,000. So here I roll down the
table that kind of shows you the rough
不需要1000次方的时间。这里我把表往下拉
difficulty of breaking down the
Diffie-Hellman protocol compared to the
给大家看大体上，比较一下破解Diffie-Hellman协议
difficulty of breaking down a cipher with
a appropriate number of bits. For example,
和破解分组密码的难度，给定合适的位数。例如
if your cipher has 80 bit keys. That would
be roughly comparable to using 1,000 bit
如果你的密码有80位密匙，那么大概需要1000位的模
modules. In other words breaking a cipher
with 80 bit keys takes time roughly 2 to the 80
换句话说，破解一个80位的密码，大约需要2的80次方的时间
which means that
breaking if you have Diffie-Hellman function with a 1,000
意味着如果你的Diffie-Hellman函数有1000位的模
bit module will take time 2 to the 80.
破解它需要2的8次方的时间
If your cipher uses 128 bit keys like AES, you should be
really using a 3,000 bit modulus,
如果你的密码使用128位密钥，比如AES，那么你应该使用3000位的模
even though nobody really does this. In reality
people would use 2,000 bit modulus. And
即时没有人真正这样做。实际中，人们使用2000位的模
then if your key is very large, like if
we're using a 256 bit AES key, then in
那么如果你的密钥非常大，比如说如果我们使用256位AES密钥
fact your modulus needs to be very, very
large. Again, you, you can really see the
那么实际上你的模需要非常大。大家可以看到
cube root effect here. We doubled the size
of our key and because of the cube root
这里的立方根的作用了。由于这个立方根的影响，我们将密钥大小翻倍时
effect, what that means is we have to
increase the size of, of our modulus by a
意味着我们必须增加模的大小，倍数为
factor of two cubed, namely a factor of
eight, which is where this 15,000 comes from.
2的立方，也就是8的倍数，这个就是15000的由来
from. And again I should mention there's
not exactly a factor of eight because of
我应该再提一下，这并不是严格的8倍
the extra constants in the exponent. So
this is a nice table that shows you that
因为指数上有其他常数项。那么这张表不错
if you're gonna be using Diffie-Hellman to
exchange, a session key. And that session
它告诉大家，如果大家使用Diffie-Hellman协议来交换会话密钥
key is gonna be used for a block cipher
with a certain key size, this table shows
用于分组密码的会话密钥要有合适的密钥大小
you what modular size you need to use so
that the security of the key exchange
这张表为大家展示了，需要使用的模的大小，使得密钥交换协议的安全性
protocol is comparable to the security of
the block cipher you're gonna be using after.
和你之后使用的分组密码的安全性相当
Now this last row should
really be disturbing to you. I should tell
现在这个最后一行应该会困扰着大家
you that working with such a large modulus
is very problematic. This is actually
我应该告诉大家，要使用如此之大的模很成问题
gonna be quite slow, and so the question
is whether there is anything better that
速度会很慢，那么问题是，我们能否做得更好
we can do? And it turns out there is. In
fact the way I describe the Diffie-Hellman
实际上是有的。事实上，我描述Diffie-Hellman函数的方法
function is I describe it at the way
Diffie and Hellman described it in 1976
正式Diffie和Hellman在1976年描述的方法
using arithmetic module of primes. The
problem with arithmetic modular primes is
使用了质数模的算术。质数模算术的问题是
that the Diffie-Hellman function is hard
to compute, but it's not as hard as you'd
Diffie-Hellman函数难以计算，但不如大家想的那么难
like. There's this cube root effect that
makes it a little easier than what you'd
有这个立方根的影响，使之比大家想的稍容易些
really like. And so the question is can we
run the Diffie-Hellman protocol in other
那么问题是，我们能否在其他的设定下，运行Diffie-Hellman协议
settings. And it turns out the answer is
yes. In fact we can literally translate
实际上答案是肯定的。事实上我们可以
the Diffie-Hellman protocol from an
arithmetic model of primes to a different
把Diffie-Hellman协议从质数模算术的设定
type of algebraic object and solving the
Diffie-Hellman problem on that other
翻译成不同类型的代数对象，然后在其它的
algebraic object is much, much harder.
This other algebraic object is what's
代数对象上解Diffie-Hellman问题将是困难的多。这个其它的代数对象就是
called an elliptic curve. And as I said,
computing the Diffie-Hellman function on
所谓的椭圆曲线。如我所说，计算定义在椭圆曲线域上的Diffie-Hellman函数
these elliptic curves is much harder than
computing the Diffie-Hellman modulo primes.
要比计算质数模乘法群上的Diffie-Hellman问题困难得多
Because the problem is so much harder, now
we can use much smaller objects in
因为问题更加困难，现在我们可以使用小得多的代数对象
particular, you know we'd be using primes
that are only a 160 bits or 80 bit keys or
特别地，我们使用仅有160位或80位或
only 512 bits for 256 bit keys. So because
these module don't grow as
512位的质数，用于256位的分组密钥。那么因为这些模
fast on elliptic curves, there's generally
a slow transition away from using module
在椭圆曲线上增长得不快，通常从使用模算术
arithmetic, to using elliptic curves. I'm
not going to describe elliptic curves
到使用椭圆曲线有一个缓慢的转换。我这里先不为大家描述椭圆曲线
right now for you, but if this is
something you'd like to learn about I can
但如果这是大家想学习的
do that at the very last week of the
course, when we discuss more advanced
我可以留到本课程的最后一周，届时讨论更多高级话题
topics. But in fact when we come back to
Diffie-Hellman next week I'm gonna describe it
但事实上当我们下周回到Diffie-Hellman时
more abstractly so that it really doesn't
matter which algebraic structure you use
我将更为抽象地描述它，这样你使用的代数结构就不重要了
whether you use arithmetic model of primes
or whether you use a elliptic curve we
无论使用质数模算术，还是使用椭圆曲线域
can kinda abstract that whole issue away
and then use the Diffie-Hellman concept a for
我们都可以将整个过程抽象出来，然后使用Diffie-Hellman这个概念
key exchange and for other things as well.
And as I said we'll see that more
进行密钥交换，以及一些其它事情。如我所说
abstractly next week. So as usual I wanna
show that this beautiful protocol that I
我们下周还会看到更多的抽象。通常我想展示这个漂亮的协议
just showed you, the Diffie-Hellman protocol,
is as is, is actually completely insecure
就像我刚刚展示给大家的，Diffie-Hellman协议对抗主动攻击时，是完全不安全的
against an active attack. Namely, it's
completely insecure against what's called
它是完全不安全的
the man in the middle attack. We need to
do something more than this protocol to
当存在所谓的中间人攻击。我们需要对这个协议
make is secure against man in the middle.
And again we're gonna come back to Diffie
做些补充，让它对中间人攻击也是安全的
Hellman and make it secure against man in
the middle next week. Okay. So let's see
让它能安全地抵抗中间人攻击。好，那现在我们看
why the protocol that I just showed you is
insecure against active attacks. Well
为什么我刚才展示给大家的这个协议对主动攻击是不安全的
suppose we have this man in the middle
that's trying to eavesdrop on the
假设我们有这个中间人，他试图窃听
conversation between Alice and Bob. Well
so, the protocol starts with Alice sending
Alice和Bob之间的会话。协议开始时
g to the a over to Bob. Well, so the man
in the middle is gonna intercept that and
Alice发送g^a给Bob。那么中间人截获了这个g^a
he's gonna take the message that Alice
sent and he's gonna replace it with his
他将取Alice发出的信息，换成他自己的信息
own message. So it's called A', And
let's write that is g to the a'.
我们记为A'，写成g^a'
Okay? So the man in the middle chooses his
own a' and what he sends to Bob is
所以中间人选择了他自己的a'
actually g to the a'. Now poor Bob
doesn't know that the man in the middle
把g^a'发送给Bob。现在可怜的Bob并不知道
actually did anything to this traffic, all
he sees is he got the value A'. As
中间人对通信流量做了手脚，他只能获得A'
far as he knows, that value came from
Alice. So what is he gonna do in response?
他目前只知道，这个值来自Alice，那他怎么回复
Well, he's gonna send back his value B out
which is g to the b back to Alice. Well
Bob会回复他的B=g^b给Alice
again the man in the middle is gonna
intercept this B. He's gonna generate his
中间人截获了这个B
own b' and what he actually sends
back to Alice is B' which is g to the b'.
他可以生成自己的b'，然后发送B'=g^b'给Alice
Okay, now what happens? Well
Alice is gonna compute her part of the
现在会怎么样呢？Alice计算她的密钥
secret key and she's gonna get g to the ab'. Bob is gonna compute his part of
她会得到g^ab'。Bob计算他的密钥
the secret key and he's gonna get g to the
b times a'. Okay, these now you
他会得到g^ba'
notice these are not the same keys. In the
man in the middle because he knows both A'
现在大家要注意，这些密钥并不一样
但是对于中间人来讲
and B' he can compute both g to
the ab' and g to ba'. Yeah it's
他既知道A'又知道B'，他既可以计算g^ab'也可以计算g^ba'
not difficult to see the man in the middle
knows both values. And as a result, now he
容易看出中间人可以知道这两个值
can basically play this man in the middle
and when Alice sends an encrypted message
这样的话，他可以扮演中间人，
当Alice给Bob发送一个加密的信息时
to Bob the man in the middle can simply
decrypt this message because he knows the
中间人可以解密这个信息
secret key that Alice encrypted message
with, re-encrypt it using Bob's key. And
因为他知道Alice加密信息的密钥
然后中间人重新使用Bob的密钥加密这个信息
then send the message on over to Bob. And
this way Alice sent the message, Bob
然后把信息发送给Bob
这样Alice发送信息给Bob
received the message. Bob thinks the
message is secure. But in fact that
Bob接收到了信息。Bob认为这个信息是安全的
message went through the man in the
middle. The man in the middle decrypted
但是实际上，这个信息经过了中间人。中间人解密信息
it, re-encrypted it for Bob. At the same
time he was able to completely read it,
然后为Bob重新加密了它。同时他可以完全知道信息内容。
modify it if he wants to, and so on. So,
the protocol becomes completely insecure
如果愿意的话，他可以修改它，等等。
所以这个协议是完全不安全的。
give n a man in the middle. And so as I
said we're gonna have to enhance the
如果有中间人的话。所以我说，我们必须加强
protocol somehow to defend against men in
the middle but it turns out that it's
这个协议来抵抗中间人攻击，
actually not that difficult to enhance and
prevent man in the middle attacks.
实际上增强和防御中间人攻击并不是很难
And we're gonna come back to that and see that
in a week or two. The last think I want to
我们这两周还会回头看这里。
最后我想做的是
do is show you an interesting property of
the Diffie-Hellman protocol. In fact, I
给大家展示一个又去的Diffie-Hellman协议的性质
want to show you that this protocol can be
viewed as a non-interactive protocol. So,
事实上我想给大家展示的是这个协议可以被视为一个
非互动协议
what do I mean by that? So Imagine we have
a whole bunch of users, you know, millions
这是什么意思呢？设想我们有一组用户
of users. Let's call them Alice, Bob,
Charlie, David and so on and so forth.
几百万用户。我们叫他们Alice，Bob，Charlie，Dvaid等等
Each one of them is going to choose a
random, secret value, and then on their
他们中每个人都会选取一个随机的私密值
Facebook profiles, they're gonna write
down, their contribution to the
然后在他们的Facebook页面上，写下他们
Diffie-Hellman protocol. Alright so
everybody just writes down you know g to
对Diffie-Hellman协议的贡献。那么每个人写下了
the a, g to the b, g to the c and so on.
Now the interesting thing about this is,
g^a,g^b,g^c...现在，有趣的是
if say Alice and Charlie wanna set up a
shared key they don't need to communicate
如果Alice和Charlie想建立一个共享密钥，他们无需相互通信
at all. Basically Alice would go and read
Charlie's public profile. Charlie would go
Alice只要去Charlie的公共页面
and read Alice's public profile. And now,
boom, they immediately have a secret key.
Charlie只要去Alice的公共页面。这样，他们就共享了一个密钥
Namely, now, Alice knows, g to the c and
a. Charlie knows g to the a and с. And as
Alice只要了g^ca，Charlie知道了g^ac
a result, both of them can compute п to
the ac. So, in some sense, once they've
因此双方都能计算g^ac，某种意义上
posted their contributions to the
Diffie-Hellman protocol to their public
一旦他们在公共页面发布了他们对Diffie-Hellman的协议的共享
profiles, they don't need to communicate
with each other at all to set up a shared key.
他们根本不需要相互通信就能建立共享密钥
They immediately have a shared key
and now they can start communicating
他们立即就能有一个共享密钥，现在他们
securely through Facebook or not with one
another. And notice that this is true for
就能通过Facebook来安全地通信了，而不会是和别人
any Facebook user. So as soon as I read
somebody's public profile, I immediately
注意这对所有Facebook用户都可以。只要我去访问某人的公共页面
have a shared key with them without ever
communicating with them. This property is
我就能迅速地得到一个共享密钥，无需相互通信
sometimes called a non-interactive
property of the Diffie-Hellman. So now, let
这个性质有时称作Diffie-Hellman的非互动性
me show you an open problem. And this is
an open problem that's been open for ages
让我给大家展示一个开放问题。这是一个开放问题
and ages and ages. So it'd be really cool
if one of you can actually solve it. The
各个时代都是这样。如果有人能解决它将是很好的
question is, can we do this for more than
two parties? In other words, say we have
问题是，我们能否对多于两方的用户做这些呢？换句话说
four parties. All of them post their
values to their Facebook profiles. And now
比如说我们有四方，所有人都在他们的Facebook
公共页面上发布了他们的值
we'd like to make it that just by reading
Facebook profiles, all of them can set up
现在我们想只通过阅读Facebook页面
a shared secret key. In other words, Alice
is, what she'll, she'll do is she'll only
所有人就可以建立共享密钥，换句话说
read the public profiles of, the three
friends, Bob, Charlie and David. And
Alice会去访问其他三个人的公共页面
already she can compute a shared key with
them. And similarly David is just gonna
她已经可以计算他们之间的共享密钥
类似的，David只需
read the public profile of Charlie. Bob
and Alice. And already he has a shared key
访问Charlie，Bob和Alice的公共页面
with all four of them. Okay, so the
question is whether we can kind of setup
他就有了他们四个的共享密钥。问题在于，
我们能否可以非互动地建立
non-interactively these, these shared keys
for groups that are larger than just two
这些共享密钥，对于多于两个人的组来说
people. So as I said, for n equals two,
this is just a Diffie-Hellman protocol. In
如我所说，n-2就是Diffie-Hellman协议
other words, if just two parties want to
set up a shared key without communicating
换句话说，如果只有双方想建立共享密钥
with one another, that's just
Diffie-Hellman. It turns out, for N equals
且无需通信，那么使用Diffle-Hellman即可
three, we also know how to do it, there's
a known protocol, it's called protocol due
实际上对于n=3的情况，我们也知道如何去做
有一个已知的协议
to Joux. It already uses very, very fancy
mathematics, much more complicated
由Joux提出，它使用了非常高级的数学知识
mathematics than what I just showed you.
And for N equals four, or five, or
比我刚刚为大家展示的要复杂多的数学知识
对于n=4或5或任何更大的数
anything above this, above four, this
problem is completely open. Nearly the
大于4的，这个问题是完全开放的
case where four people post something to
the public profiles and then everybody
在这个情况下，4人在他们的公共页面上发布信息
else reads the public profile and then
they have a joint shared key, this is
这样别人可以访问这些公共页面，然后他们就有了
一个公有的共享密钥
something we don't know how to do even for
four people. And this is a problem that's
即使只有4个人，我们也不知道怎么做
been open for ages and ages, it's kind of
a fun problem to think about and so see if
这在各个时代都是一个开放的问题，是个有趣的问题
you can solve it, if you will, it's
instant fame in the crypto world. Okay, so
值得去思考，如果你能解决它，就会立即在密码学界获得名气
I'll stop here, and we'll continue with
another key exchange mechanism in the next segment.
到此为止，下节我们会继续讲另一个密钥交换机制